Elena Gutiérrez

Email elena.gutierrez@imdea.org
Website http://software.imdea.org/~elena.gutierrez/

Address IMDEA Software Institute

Office 342

Campus de Montegancedo s/n 28223 - Pozuelo de Alarcón

Madrid, Spain

About Me

I am a 4^{th} -year Ph.D. student at the IMDEA Software Institute in Madrid, supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty, expecting to graduate before October 2020.

My research interests are mainly focused on the theory of finite and weighted automata and its applications to software verification and machine learning.

Before joining IMDEA, I studied a Double Degree in Mathematics and Computer Science at Universidad Autónoma de Madrid.

Research Experience

Sept. 2016 -Present

IMDEA Software Institute and Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

PhD. in Software, Systems and Computing supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

Working on the language-theoretical aspects of finite and weighted automata constructions including pushdown automata and weighted context-free languages; learning-automata, minimization and other optimization algorithms for finite automata and weighted automata.

May. 2019 -Nov. 2019

National Institute of Informatics in Tokyo (Japan)

6-month internship supervised by Prof. Ichiro Hasuo

Developing a genetic-algorithm-based metaheuristic (in C) for solving the problem of finding the word with the highest weight in a weighted automaton over the reals. The goal is to use it in combination with a procedure that translates recurrent neural networks into weighed automata to enable an efficient analysis of these networks.

2013 - IMDEA Software Institute

3-month summer internships supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

Exploring the use of Horn clauses for the formal verification of programs. As a result I developed a Prolog algorithm that translates non-linear logic programs into linear preserving their meaning.

Publications

2020	Genetic Algorithm for the Weighted Maximization Problem on Weighted Automata E. Gutiérrez, T. Okudono, M. Waga and I. Hasuo. Published in GECCO 2020
2019	A Congruence-based Perspective on Automata Minimization Algorithms
	P. Ganty, E. Gutiérrez and P. Valero. Published in MFCS 2019
2018	The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars
	P. Ganty and E. Gutiérrez. Published in FSTTCS 2018
2017	Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata
	P. Ganty and E. Gutiérrez. Published in FCT 2017

Bachelor's Thesis

2016 Linearisation of Index Bounded Sets of Horn Clauses.

Supervised by Prof. Pierre Ganty

A Prolog algorithm that transforms non-linear logic programs into linear preserving their meaning.

Education

2016 - PhD. in Software Systems and Computing

Present Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

Expected graduation date: October 2020

2011 - Double Degree in Mathematics and Computer Science (360 ECTS)

2016 Universidad Autónoma de Madrid | Average Grade (out of 10) - 8.2

Languages

English Fluent TOEFL iBT (Feb. 2016). Total (out of 120): 104

Spanish Native **French** Basic

Programing Languages

• Most experienced with: C, Prolog, Python and LaTeX

• Some experience with: Haskell, C++, HTML, Shell

Grants

2017-2021 Predoctoral Contract for PhD. Training Grant (FPI)

Provided by the Spanish Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competitiveness

Schools/Seminars Attended

- womENcourage 2018, ACM Celebration of Women in Computing. 3–5, October, 2018. Belgrade, Serbia.
- 2nd School on Formal Verification by The Hebrew University. 17–21, December, 2017. Jerusalem, Israel.
- Microsoft Research PhD. Summer School. 4-8, July, 2016. Cambridge, UK.

Conference/Public Talks

June, 2020	A Congruence-based Perspective on Automata Minimization Algorithms Presentation at the Séminaire de l'équipe Méthodes Formelles at LaBRI. June 23 rd , 2020
June, 2020	A Congruence-based Perspective on Automata Minimization Algorithms S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. June 16 th , 2020
Aug., 2019	A Congruence-based Perspective on Automata Minimization Algorithms Presentation at MFCS 2019 in Aachen, Germany. August 29 th , 2019
March, 2019	Undecidability and Context-Free Languages S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. March 25 th , 2019
Feb., 2019	¿Cómo garantizar que un programa hace lo que esperas?" I+D+M². Mujeres en Montegancedo. February 11 th , 2019
Dec., 2018	The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars Presentation at FSTTCS 2018 in Ahmedabad, India. December 12 th , 2018
Sept., 2018	The Parikh Property for Weighted Context-Free Grammars Formal Methods and Verification Seminar at Université Libre de Bruxelles. Sept. 26 th , 2018

April, 2018 Weighted Context-Free Grammars: Does Parikh's Theorem still hold?
S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. April 3rd, 2018

Sept., 2017 Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata
Presentation at FCT 2017 in Bordeaux, France. September 11th, 2017

March, 2017 Parikh Image of Pushdown Automata
S3, Seminar Series at Imdea Software Institute. March 7th, 2017

Additional Information

Teaching Support classes for students at secondary education

experience Mathematics, English, Physics and Chemistry

Volunteer AFS International ONG

work Coordination of exchange activities for foreign students in Spain

Soñar Despierto Foundation

Support classes for students coming from marginalized backgrounds

Interests Running (medium: 10 km, and long: 21 km distances)